<unit id="python_unit" title="Unit 2:  Python and ML" version="1.0">
    

    <question qtag="ODE Solver" preferred_model="gpt-5.4-mini">
        <question_text><![CDATA[
        <p>Write a Python function that implements a first-order Euler solution to the ODE:
        \[
        \frac{dx}{dt} = -a\,x(t) + b\,x(t)^2
        \]
        </p>

        <p>
            The function should take the initial condition, the parameters, the time step,
            and the number of steps. It should return the full trajectory of \(x(t)\) as
            an <code>ndarray</code>.
        </p>
        ]]></question_text>

        <solution><![CDATA[
        <p>One correct solution is:</p>

        <pre><code>def sim(x0, a, b, tstep, nsteps):
        x = np.zeros(nsteps + 1)
        x[0] = x0
        for i in range(nsteps):
            f = -a * x[i] + b * x[i] ** 2
            x[i + 1] = x[i] + tstep * f
        return x</code></pre>
        ]]></solution>

        <partial_credit>true</partial_credit>
        <required>true</required>
        <parts>
            <part>
                <part_label>all</part_label>
                <points>10</points>
            </part>
        </parts>

        <rubrics>
            <item id="arguments" part="all" point_adjustment="+4">
                <display_text>Complete function interface</display_text>
                <condition>Student includes the initial condition, model parameters, time step, and number of 
                    steps as inputs.  If they supply some of the inputs but not all, award partial credit.</condition>
                <notes>Different variable names, argument order, and omission of type hints are acceptable.</notes>
            </item>

            <item id="correct_update" part="all" point_adjustment="+4">
                <display_text>Correct Euler update</display_text>
                <condition>Student implements the mathematically correct Euler step for the given ODE.</condition>
                <notes>Any equivalent implementation of the same update should receive this credit.</notes>
            </item>

            <item id="returns_array" part="all" point_adjustment="+2">
                <display_text>Returns the full trajectory as an ndarray</display_text>
                <condition>Student returns an array containing all iterates, not only the final value.  If returning a list, award only 1 point.</condition>
            </item>
            <item id="syntax_incorrect" part="all" point_adjustment="-2">
                <display_text>Minor Python syntax errors</display_text>
                <condition>Student's solution has minor Python syntax errors that do not obscure the intended algorithm. </condition>
            </item>
        </rubrics>
        <rubric_total>sum_positive</rubric_total> <!-- sets score exactly equal to the sum of point adjustments -->

        <grading_notes><![CDATA[
        Any mathematically correct Euler implementation that satisfies the specification should receive full credit.
        Do not require the exact variable names used in the reference solution.
        If the student omits an explicit NumPy import but the intended use of ndarray is otherwise clear, do not penalize that separately.
        ]]></grading_notes>
    </question>
    
    <question qtag="Logistic regression" preferred_model="gpt-4.1-mini">
        <question_text><![CDATA[
        <p>Consider a logistic regression model for binary classification with a scalar feature \(x\) and parameters \(w\) and \(b\):
        \[
        p = Pr(y=1|x) = \sigma(wx + b) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-(wx + b)}}
        \]
        </p>

        <ol type="a">
            <li>Find the \(w\) and \(b\) that \(p=0.5\) when \(x=0\) and \(p=0.8\) when \(x=1\). </li>
            <li>What is the value of \(p\) when \(x=0.5\) using the parameters found in part (a)?</li>
        </ol>

        ]]></question_text>

        <solution><![CDATA[
        <p>a) To find \(w\) and \(b\), we can set up the equations based on the given conditions:  Let \(z = wx + b\).</p>
        <p>When \(x=0\), \(p=0.5 \implies z = 0 \implies b = 0\).</p>
        <p>When \(x=1\), \(p=0.8 \implies z = \ln\left(\frac{0.8}{0.2}\right) \implies w = \ln(4) \approx 1.386\).</p>
        <p>b) Using the parameters found in part (a), when \(x=0.5\), \(p = \sigma(1.386 \cdot 0.5 + 0) \approx 0.667\).</p>

        ]]></solution>
        <parts>
            <part>
                <part_label>a</part_label>
                <points>5</points>
            </part>
            <part>
                <part_label>b</part_label>
                <points>5</points>
            </part>
        </parts>

        <partial_credit>true</partial_credit>
        <required>true</required>
       

        <rubrics>
            <item id="linear_system" part="a" point_adjustment="+3">
                <display_text>Linear system of equations</display_text>
                <condition>Correctly identified that the problem can be solved by setting up a linear system of equations based on the given conditions.</condition>
                <notes>Simply writing the equations without solving them is sufficient for the full point award credit.</notes>
            </item>

            <item id="solution_param" part="a" point_adjustment="+2">
                <display_text>Correct solution</display_text>
                <condition>Student implements the mathematically correct solution for the given problem.</condition>
                <notes>No work needs to be shown if the final answer is correct. If the solution is correct except for minor errors, award 1 point.</notes>
            </item>

            <item id="solution_prob" part="b" point_adjustment="+5">
                <display_text>Correct probability calculation</display_text>
                <condition>Student correctly calculates the probability for the given input using the parameters found in part (a).  Partial credit if the 
                calculation is set up correctly but the final numerical answer is incorrect.
                Minor algebraic mistakes may be ignored for partial credit.</condition>
            </item>
        </rubrics>
        <rubric_total>sum_positive</rubric_total> <!-- sets score exactly equal to the sum of point adjustments -->

        <grading_notes><![CDATA[
        Any mathematically correct solution that satisfies the specification should receive full credit.
        ]]></grading_notes>
    </question>

    <question qtag="Gradient Descent" preferred_model="gpt-4.1-mini">
        <question_text><![CDATA[
        <p>Consider the function \(f(x)\) shown in the figure below.  Gradient descent is
        run with a learning rate of \(\alpha\) starting from the initial point \(x_0\).</p>

        <img src="/pkg_assets/unit2_images/func.png" alt="Function to perform gradient descent" width="400"/>


        <ol type="a">
            <li>What are the local minima of the function \(f(x)\)?</li>
            <li> For each local minima, describe the set of initial points \(x_0\) that would converge to that minima under gradient descent with small \(\alpha\).</li>
        </ol>
        ]]></question_text>
        <solution><![CDATA[
        <ol type="a">
            <li>The local minima of the function \(f(x)\) are approximately at \(x = 1\) and \(x = 4\).</li>
            <li> Since the local maxima is at \(x = 2\), the set of initial points \(x_0\) that would converge to the local minimum at \(x = 1\) is approximately \(x_0 < 2\), and the set of initial points that would converge to the local minimum at \(x = 4\) is approximately \(x_0 > 2\).</li>
        ]]></solution>  
        <parts>
            <part>
                <part_label>a</part_label>
                <points>4</points>
            </part>
            <part>
                <part_label>b</part_label>
                <points>6</points>
            </part>
        </parts>
        <partial_credit>true</partial_credit>
        <required>true</required>
        <rubrics>
            <item id="identify_minima" part="a" point_adjustment="+4">
                <display_text>Identify local minima</display_text>
                <condition>Student correctly identifies the local minima of the function based on the provided figure.</condition>
                <notes>Minor inaccuracies in the exact location of the minima may be ignored for partial credit.</notes>
            </item>

            <item id="describe_convergence" part="b" point_adjustment="+6">
                <display_text>Describe convergence regions</display_text>
                <condition>Student correctly describes the regions of initial points that would converge to each local minimum under gradient descent with a small learning rate.</condition>
                <notes>Partial credit may be awarded if the student correctly identifies one of the convergence regions or provides a qualitatively correct description.</notes>
            </item>
        </rubrics>
        <rubric_total>sum_positive</rubric_total>
    </question>

    

    
    
</unit>
